Guide to the Janet Fitchen papers.
Fitchen, Janet papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Janet Fitchen papers.
4952
Janet M. Fitchen.
15 cubic ft.
Files, notes, correspondence, transcripts, manuscripts, maps, testimony.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Subject files, research and field notes, correspondence, data and data analysis, transcripts, case files, manuscripts of books, maps, testimony, and other papers relating to Fitchen's work on rural poverty, mostly in New York State.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Cultural anthropologist who concentrated on the rural United States. She wrote "Poverty in Rural America: A Case Study," an ethnographic study of poverty in upstate New York and "Endangered Spaces, Enduring Places: Change, Identity, and Survival in Rural America," which describes changes now transforming rural communities in the Northeast. In 1992-93, she was an Associate with the Western Rural Development Center in Corvallis, Oregon, where she conducted research on rural poverty in several other regions of the United States. She taught in the Anthropology Department at Ithaca College and the Department of Rural Sociology at Cornell University. She was a consultant and trainer for human service programs around the nation, including community action programs, social service agencies, and Cooperative Extension as well as Head Start and rural school districts, as well as serving on several national and state advisory boards related to rural poverty.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Subject files, research and field notes, correspondence, data and data analysis, transcripts, case files, manuscripts of books, maps, testimony, and other papers relating to Fitchen's work on rural poverty, mostly in New York State.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Fitchen, Janet M.
Subjects:
Rural poor--New York (State)--Study and teaching.
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Restricted.
CONTAINER LIST
- Lectures, workshops, and talks
  - Allegany Talk, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rural Human Services Talk/Workshops, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Public Talks, Workshops, Guest Lectures, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - College and Community Lectures, 192 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The James Mickel Williams Lecture (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hunger-Poverty Talks (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Association for Rural Mental Health - Keynote "When Communities Collapse: Implications for Rural America", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Presentation to President's Council on Rural America, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Testimony for NYS Senate Social Services Committee, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Anthropological Association Presentation, "Changing Communities in Rural America", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Testimony for the House Select Committee on Children, Youth, and Families, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rural Sociological Society Task Force - Rural Poverty, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Congressional Colloquium, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Congressional Colloquium, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Community Visits (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cornell University Talk, "Residential Mobility and Urban to Rural...", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cornell Rural Sociology Presentation, "More Poverty in Upstate N.Y. ...", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - R.S.S. Talk, "Rural Poverty and Policy Research", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - R.S.S. Talk, "Redistribution of Poverty...", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Pathways from Poverty", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Welfare Reform, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Rural Studies Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - AAA Panel, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Corvallis Conference on Rural Poverty, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Children in Poverty Conference, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - NY State Education Department Conference, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Presentations, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Forest Service Conference - Ithaca, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Anthropology/Sociology Seminar Presentations, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Teen Parenting/Teen Pregnancy, "Women and Children at Risk" Presentation, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Rural Rensselaer County Council - Rural Women Conference, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cooperative Extension, "When Rural Communities Collapse...", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Farm Family Seminar - Albany, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - R.S.S. Panel, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - American Anthropological Association Panel, "Changing Indentity in Rural Communities in the United States", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - R.S.S. Session - Heterogeneity, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - R.S.S. Ethics Panel, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Poverty Research Conference - Penn State, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Rural Household Livelihood Strategies - Penn State, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Pennsylvania Rural County Caucus Assembly, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Aspen Institute Rural Poverty Research Meeting, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Wye Conference Aspen Institute - Research Needs in Rural Poverty, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Wye Conference, "White Poverty in Upstate N.Y.", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "Agricultural Trends Affecting Rural Communities", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - US/European Symposium, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Conference on Communities and Watershed Planning - Cornell University, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Summer Institute, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Summer Institute - National Rural Studies Committee (NRSC), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - NRSC Summer Institute Materials, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Presentation, "A Framework for Analyzing Poverty of Rural People and Places", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - E.F.N.E.P. Expanded Food and Nutrition Education Program Workshops, "The Aide and the Homemaker", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - E.F.N.E.P. Workshop Questionnaire Tabulation, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - E.F.N.E.P. Analysis of Program, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - E.F.N.E.P. Materials from Workshops - Alaska, Oklahoma, Arizona, Montana, Tennessee, Ohio, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - E.F.N.E.P. Workshops - West Virginia, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - E.F.N.E.P. - North Dakota, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence - Workshop Related, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - E.F.N.E.P. Correspondence, etc., 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Writings
  - An Abiding Place, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Instructions for National Rural Studies Committee Book Chapter, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Book: Homelessness in America: A Reference Connection; Information on Fitchen's Chapter, "The Case of Rural Homelessness", 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Review of Chapter from Endangered Spaces, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Westview Press - Endangered Spaces, Enduring Places: Change, Identity, and Survival in Rural America, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Publicity for Book, Endangered Spaces, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Mailing List - Copies of Endangered Spaces, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Westview Press - Endangered Spaces, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Endangered Spaces - Book Reviews, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Book: Reviews, Responses, and Correspondence for Endangered Spaces, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Brainstorming for Possible Book on Rural Poverty, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Material Related to Rural Poverty: An Anthropological Case Study in New York, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence - Book, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Book Revision - Poverty in Rural America, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Book Review - Poverty in Rural America, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Poverty Book - Outline, Drafts, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Poverty Chapter for Mil Duncan's Book, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - College Anthropology Papers, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Undergraduate Thesis, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The People of Road Junction", 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Paper - College, "The Ambivalent Role of Local Political Leaders in East and British Central Africa", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - College Papers - University of Illinois, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "A Day with Mary Cronin," Revised - College, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Role of Women in East Africa..." [Janet Matthews] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "A Community Study of Philo, Illinois," University of Illinois, JMF, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Critical Review of a Study of Values," Vassar College, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Clifford S. Rich," Ph.D. Work at Cornell University, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Northeastern Anthropological Association Paper - "The Single Parent Family", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Paper - Society for Applied Anthropology, "Rural Poverty in Northern Appalachia", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Anthropological Association Paper: "Family and Neighborhood in a Rural Depressed Area, USA", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Special Housing Problems of the Rural Poor", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Individualism," Current Working Version of Paper, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Hunger in Amercia," Public Version, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Protecting Privacy in Action-Oriented Fieldwork", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Society for Applied Anthropology Paper, "Applying Anthropological Perspectives to Anti-Poverty Programs", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - A.A.A. Paper, "Anthropology in Human Service Programs", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - N.E.A.A. Paper, "Social Impacts of Agricultural Change...", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rural Sociological Society Paper, "Rural Poverty and School Child...", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - R.S.S. Paper, "Residential Mobility as a Form of Homelessness in Rural N.Y.", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - R.S.S. Paper for "Sonya Panel", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - R.S.S. Method, "How Do You Know What to Ask...", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - R.S.S. Paper, "Natives and Newcomers in Rural N.Y.", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - S.F.A.A. Paper, "Agricultural Change and Rural Society in the U.S.", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - A.A.A. Paper, "Homelessness in Rural America...", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - S.F.A.A. Paper, "Reciprocity in Rural Poverty Research", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - A.A.A. Paper, "Rural Poverty and Welfare Reform...", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - S.F.A.A. Paper, "Reciporcity in Rural Poverty Research", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - A.A.A. "Changing Communities in Rural America", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Paper - Karen A. Curtis, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - A.A.A. Paper, "Rural Poverty and Welfare Program...", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Rural Poverty and Residential Mobility...", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - S.F.A.A. Paper, "Poverty and the 'Single Parent Family'", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - R.S.S. Paper, "Poverty and the 'Single Parent Family'", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - S.F.A.A. Paper, "Diversity Without Development...", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - A.A.A. Paper, "Impoverization of Rural U.S. Communities through Exchange Migration", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous Poverty Thoughts, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mobility, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Mobility - Outline, Materials for Previous Papers, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Originals of Current Papers - J.M.F., 1994 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Outline for Case Descriptions, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Paper Sent to Human Organization for Publication, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous Work, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - R.S.S. Paper, "Spatial Redistribution of Poverty...", 1995 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Paper - "A Cultural Anthropologist at Work in America", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Paper - Adapted from Endangered Spaces, "Low-Level Radioactive Waste Disposal", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Paper - University of Illinois, "'Peasantry' as a Social Type", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Paper based on Keynote Address, "A Time of Change in Rural Communities", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Possible Paper, "Welfare Reform for Rural America", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - S.F.A.A. Paper, "Single-Parent Family", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Human Services in the Rural Environment Paper, "When Communities Collapse", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Paper, "Toxic Chemcal Pollution of Residential Areas", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "Residential Mobility Among the Rural Poor", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - R.S.S. Paper, "Agricultural Change, Community Change, and Rural Poverty", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "The Dynamics of Rural Impoverization", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - S.F.A.A. "Anthropological Work in Environmental Problems in U.S. - The Case of Groundwater Contamination", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - N.R.S.C. Paper, "A Geographic Sampler of Rural Poverty", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "Rural Poverty and Residential Mobility", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - N.R.S.C., 1991 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Paper, "Cultural Values Affecting Risk Perception", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "The Academic Community and the Image of Limited Good", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, A-C, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence, D-F, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence, G-K, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence, L-Q, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence, R-S, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence, T-V, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence, W-Z, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence, Professor Emilia Martinez-Brawley, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Allegany - Current and Planned, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence, Laura B. Chodus - Regent, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Correspondence, Mark Cohen, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Correspondence Addresses (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Correspondence, General, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Correspondence, Mississippi State, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Research related
  - North County G.N.L. Planning, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Allegany County Field Notes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - State Write-Ups, Research Notes, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mobility - 20 Departments of Social Services Cases - Allegany County, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mobility Aspen Research - Questionnaire: D.S.S. Resdiential, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mobility - Aspen Research - Questionnaires: Headstart, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mobility - Aspen Research - Questionnaire Possibilities, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - N.Y. Questionnaire Respondents, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - N.Y. Questionnaires - Respondents, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mark Cohen, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Steuben Addison Elementary School Data, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Research Description - Research on Rural Poverty, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Research for Book - List of Interviews, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Data Sources - Field Notes - Allegany, Chenango, Delaware, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - United States Notes on Visits, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - North Carolina Field Notes, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Northern California Field Notes, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sentence Completion Survey, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Sentence Completion Survey, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - New Mexico Arrangements to Conduct Research, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - New Mexico Borderlands Research Notes, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - New Mexico Research Pueblos, etc., 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - New Mexico - TX Research Borderlands/Reading Material, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - New Mexico Research San Miguel - Mora, 1988-1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - New Mexico Research Income and Poverty Status, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Research Write-Ups, Analysis, Ideas, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Field Notes II, 19701-1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Field Notes III, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous Research, 19992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Economic Research Service Materials, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Personal and miscellaneous files
  - Personal File - Vita, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Candidacy Examination to Cornell University for J.M. Fitchen, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Personal/Employment Ithaca College, Cornell University, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Personal File Cornell Appointments, 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Personal File Cornell Contacts, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Personal File Cornell Position, 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Personal File Cornell University Rural Sociology Department, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Personal File Cornell University Anthropology Department, 1976-1989 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Material for Tenure, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Personal File Western Rural Development Center/National Rural Studies Committee Center Associate, 1991-1999 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - N.R.S.C. Center Associate Activities, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - School Board Material (Previously Located in 3-Ring Binder), 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - CARDI - Community and Rural Development Institute, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Articles Sent to J.M.F. for Review - Rural Sociology, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Peer Review, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Rural poverty video, 1974-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Student file: Jayne Spring (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Student file: Myram Contiguglia, Diane Crews, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Rural Poverty - newspaper clippings, reports from around the U.S., contacts with reporters, 1987-1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Grants, proposals, etc., 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1986; 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Rural Poverty" chapters I-VII (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Rural Poverty" chapters VIII-end (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Food and Foodways article, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Journal of Rural Community Psychology, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Urban Anthropology, Summer, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rural Sociologist article, 1988; 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Practicing Anthropology, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Human Organization, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Cooperative Extension program, Tuskegee University, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Featured publications, 1960-1991 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - The Outreach Manual, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Working with Families, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)